Desmond C. Ong

Stanford University Department of Psychology Jordan Hall, Building 01-420 450 Serra Mall Stanford, CA 94305 email: dco@cs.stanford.edu website: web.stanford.edu/~dco/ github: github.com/desmond-ong

Last Updated: February 2017

Research Interests

My core research interests are in <u>Computational Affective Cognition</u>: building computational models of how humans reason about emotions. At a basic level, I distill insights from affective science and cognitive psychology into formal and precise models of reasoning about emotions. At a more applied level, I apply these models to study mental disorders (computational psychiatry) and to improve computational agents (affective computing/robotics).

In my work, I take an interdisciplinary approach grounded in cognitive science and affective science, along with tools from computer science (machine learning; natural language processing) and behavioral economics (economic games and analyses).

Education

2017 Ph.D., Cognitive Psychology and Affective Science, Stanford University

(Expected)

Thesis Advisors: Noah D. Goodman, Jamil Zaki

2017 M.S., Computer Science, Stanford University

(Expected)

2014 M.A., Psychology, Stanford University

2011 B.A., Economics (summa cum laude; top in class),

and Physics (magna cum laude; top three in class),

with minors in Cognitive Studies; and in Information Science,

Cornell University

Professional Appointments

2011 – 2012 Research Engineer

Data Storage Institute (DSI),

Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), Singapore

2007 – 2008 Research Intern (Full-time)

Institute of Materials Research and Engineering (IMRE),

Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), Singapore

Awards, Honors, Fellowships

2015 Computational Social Science Fellowship, Institute for Research in the Social Sciences, Stanford

2014 Society for Personality and Social Psychology Graduate Student Travel Award

2012 National Science Scholarship: PhD (NSS-PhD).

Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), Singapore

Funding period: 2012 - 2017

Full tuition and stipend support for graduate studies.

2011 Paul Hartman Prize in Applied Physics, Cornell

Awarded for outstanding work in experimental physics by an undergraduate in Physics or Applied Physics.

2011 Omicron Delta Epsilon

International Honor Society in Economics

2011 Phi Beta Kappa

Honor Society in the Arts and Sciences

2011 A*STAR Chairman's Honours List

For outstanding academic performance

2009 Hunter R. Rawlings III Cornell Presidential Research Scholarship.

Funding period: 2009 - 2011

Undergraduate research scholarship with a research grant of \$5,000.

2006 National Science Scholarship: B.S. (NSS-BS).

Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR), Singapore

Funding period: 2008 - 2011

Full tuition and stipend support for undergraduate studies.

Research Grants

6. "Annotating a corpus of emotional narratives"

Dissertation Research Funds, Department of Psychology, Stanford,

2015 - 2016, US\$4,000

5. "Continuous Multimodal Emotion Inference"

Computational Social Science Fellowship Grant,

Institute for Research in the Social Sciences, Stanford

2015 - 2016, US\$10,000

4. "Studying the determinants of paying it forward"

Norman H. Anderson Research Grant, Department of Psychology, Stanford,

2012 - 2013, US\$1,000

3. "Serial Reciprocity: What makes us want to 'pass it on'?"

Einhorn Discovery Grant, College of Arts and Sciences, Cornell,

2010 - 2011, US\$870

2. "Serial Reciprocity: What makes us want to 'pass it on'?"

College of Arts and Sciences Undergraduate Research Grant, Cornell,

2010 - 2011, US\$300

1. "Studying packing in asymmetric dimer particles"

Hunter R. Rawlings III Cornell Presidential Research Scholarship, Cornell,

2009 - 2011, US\$5,000

Publications

Links to publications, code, and data can be found on my website

- Ong, D. C., Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J. (in press). Happier than thou: An egocentric positivity bias in emotional state attribution. *Emotion*.
- Chen, P., Chavez, O., Ong, D. C., & Gunderson, B. (in press). Strategic Resource Use for Learning: A Self-administered Intervention that Guides Effective Resource Use Enhances Academic Performance. Psychological Science.
- 13. Ong, D. C., Zaki, J., & Gruber, J. (2017). Increased cooperative behavior across remitted bipolar I

- disorder and major depression: Insights utilizing a behavioral economic trust game. *Journal of Abnormal Psychology*, 126(1), 1-7.
- 12. Nook, E., **Ong**, **D. C.**, Morelli, S. A., Mitchell, J. P., & Zaki, J. (2016). Prosocial Conformity: Social norms motivate broad generosity and empathy. *Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin*, 42(8), 1045-1062.
- 11. **Ong, D. C.,** Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D. (2016). Emotions in lay explanations of behavior. *Proceedings of the 38th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society*, 360-365.
- 10. **Ong, D. C.***, Asaba, M.*, & Gweon, H. (2016). Young children and adults integrate past expectations and current outcomes to reason about others' emotions. *Proceedings of the 38th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society*, 135-140.
 - * equal contribution
- 9. Devlin, H. C., Zaki., J., **Ong, D. C.**, & Gruber, J. (2016). Tracking the emotional highs, but missing the lows: Hypomania Risk is associated with positively biased empathic accuracy inference. *Cognitive Therapy and Research*, 40(1), 72-79.
- 8. **Ong, D. C.**, Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D. (2015) Affective Cognition: Modeling reasoning about emotion. *Cognition*, 143. 141-162
- 7. **Ong, D. C.**, Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J. (2015). Near-misses sting even when they are uncontrollable. *Proceedings of the 37th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society*, 1775-1780.
- Phillips, J.*, Ong, D. C.*, Surtees, A. D. R., Xin, Y., Williams, S., Saxe, R., & Frank, M. C. (2015). A second look at automatic false belief representation: reconsidering Kovács, Téglás, and Endress (2010). *Psychological Science*, 26, 1353-1367.
 * equal contribution
- 5. Devlin, H. C., Zaki., J., **Ong, D. C.**, & Gruber, J. (2014). Not as Good as You Think? Trait Positive Emotion is Associated with Increased Self-Reported Empathy but Decreased Empathic Performance. *PLOS ONE*, 9 (10), e110470

Previous work in physics and optics

- 4. Leahy, B. D., Cheng, X., **Ong**, **D. C.**, Liddell-Watson, C., & Cohen, I. (2013) Enhancing rotational diffusion using oscillatory shear. *Physical Review Letters*, **110**, 228301.
- 3. **Ong**, **D. C.**, Solanki, S., Liang, X., & Xu, X. W. (2012). Analysis of laser speckle severity, granularity, and anisotropy using the power spectral density in polar-coordinate representation. *Optical Engineering*, **51**, 054301.
- 2. Gerbode, S. J., **Ong**, **D. C.**, Liddell, C. M., & Cohen, I. (2010). Dislocations and vacancies in two-dimensional mixed crystals of spheres and dimers. *Physical Review E*, **82**, 041404.
- 1. Gerbode, S. J., Agarwal, U., **Ong**, **D. C.**, Liddell, C. M., Escobedo, F., & Cohen, I. (2010). Glassy dislocation dynamics in 2-D colloidal dimer crystals. *Physical Review Letters*, **105**, 078301.

Manuscripts under review

- Williams, W. C., Morelli, S. A., **Ong, D. C.**, & Zaki, J. (revise and resubmit). Interpersonal emotion regulation: Implications for affiliation, perceived support, relationships, and well-being.
- Morelli, S. A., **Ong, D. C.**, Makati, R., Jackson, M. O., & Zaki, J. (under review). Empathy and social support in real-world college freshmen dormitories.

Manuscripts in preparation

Ong, D. C., Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D. (in prep). Computational models of emotion in Theory of

Mind.

- **Ong, D. C.**, & Kao, J. T. (in prep). Predicting mood transitions from natural text interactions in an online social network.
- **Ong, D. C.**, Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D. (in prep). A primer to automated emotion inference from natural language text.
- Ong, D. C., Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J. (in prep). A comprehensive cross-disciplinary survey of multimodal emotion inference and sentiment analysis.

Conference Symposia and Talks

Chaired Conference Symposia

- 5. Symposium: How people think they're better than others and why it matters: consequences for social relationships, emotions, the courtroom, and online romance.
 - Chairs: Ong, D. C., & Hughes, B. L.
 - Contributed symposium at the Seventeenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social Psychology, San Diego, CA, January 2016.
 - Speakers: Clayton Critcher, Desmond Ong, Mark Alicke, Emily Yeh
 - Ong, D. C., Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J. (January 2016). Happier than thou: an egocentric positivity bias in emotion attribution. Talk given at the Seventeenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social Psychology, San Diego, CA.
- Symposium: Understanding Affective Cognition: Frontiers in modeling reasoning about others' emotions
 - Chairs: Ong, D. C., Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D.
 - Contributed symposium at the 36th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society, Quebec City, QC, Canada, July 2014.
 - Speakers: Amy Skerry, Desmond Ong, Yang Wu, Andrew Meltzoff
 - Ong, D. C., Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D. (July 2014). Modeling lay theories of emotion attribution. Talk given at the 36th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society, Quebec City, QC, Canada.

Contributed Conference Talks

- 3. **Ong, D. C.**, Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J. (July 2015). Near-misses sting even when they are uncontrollable. Talk given at the 37th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society, Pasadena, CA.
- Ong, D. C., Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D. (February 2015). Modeling lay theories of emotion attribution. Talk in symposium ("Beliefs About Emotion: Outcomes at the Individual, Interpersonal, and Cultural Levels") at the Sixteenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Long Beach, CA.
- Ong, D. C, Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J. (February 2014). Differences in intuitive theories of emotion along psychological distance. Talk given at the Emotion Preconference of the Fifteenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Austin, TX.

Contributed Posters and other presentations

25. Asaba, M., **Ong, D. C.**, & Gweon, H. (April 2017). Young children and adults integrate past expectations and current outcomes to reason about others' emotions. Poster presented by M. Asaba at the 2017 Biennial Meeting of the Society for Research in Child Development, Austin, TX.

- 24. Makati, R., Morelli, S., **Ong, D. C.**, Jackson, M. O., & Zaki, J. (January 2016). Empathy and Extraversion: Key Predictors of Connectedness and Wellbeing in Social Networks. Poster presented by R. Makati at the Seventeenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social Psychology, San Diego, CA.
- 23. Nook, E. C., **Ong, D. C.**, Morelli, S. A., Mitchell, J. P., & Zaki, J. (May 2014). Prosocial conformity: Persistence, generalization, and boundary conditions. Poster presented by E. Nook at the 26th Annual Convention of the Association for Psychological Science (APS), San Francisco, CA.
- 22. **Ong, D. C.,** Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J (April 2014). First and Third Person Intuitive Theories of Emotion. Poster presented at the Inaugural Meeting of the Society for Affective Science, Bethesda, MD.
- 21. Devlin, H. C., Zaki., J., **Ong, D. C**., & Gruber, J. (February 2014). Not as Good as You Think? Trait Positive Emotion is Associated with Increased Empathic Confidence but Decreased Empathic Performance. Poster presented by H. C. Devlin at the Fifteenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Austin, TX.
- Ong, D. C, Goodman, N. D., & Zaki, J. (February 2014). Bayesian Integration of Emotional Cues.
 Poster presented at the Fifteenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social
 Psychology, Austin, TX.
 SPSP Graduate Student Travel Award
- 19. **Ong, D. C**, Zaki, J, & Goodman, N.D. (October 2013). Computational Affective Cognition: Modeling reasoning about emotions. Poster presented at Computational Psychiatry 2013, Miami, FL.
- 18. **Ong**, **D. C.**, Zaki, J., & Goodman, N. D. (January 2013). Building a computational model of emotion inference. Poster presented at the Emotion Preconference of the Fourteenth Annual Meeting of the Society for Personality and Social Psychology, New Orleans, LA.

Previous work in physics and vision

- 17. Leahy, B., Cheng, X., **Ong**, **D. C.**, Liddell-Watson, C. & Cohen, I. (October 2013). Enhancing rotational diffusion using oscillatory shear. Presented by B. Leahy at the 85th Annual Meeting of the Society of Rheology, Montréal, QC.
- 16. Leahy, B., **Ong, D.**, Cheng, X., & Cohen, I. (March 2013). Revisiting Taylor Dispersion: Differential enhancement of rotational and translational diffusion under oscillatory shear. Presented by B. Leahy at the American Physical Society March Meeting 2013, Baltimore, MD.
- 15. Ong, D. C., Hayes, A., & Field, D. J. (May 2012). Contour change detection in the periphery: threshold as a function of temporal interval. Poster presented at the 12th Annual Meeting of the Vision Sciences Society, Naples, FL.
 Travel Grant awarded by the Cognitive Science Program @ Cornell
- 14. Field, D. J., **Ong, D. C.**, & Hayes, A. (May 2012). Translation invariance with a contour integration task. Poster presented at the 12th Annual Meeting of the Vision Sciences Society, Naples, FL. *Co-presenter
 - Travel Grant awarded by the Cognitive Science Program @ Cornell
- 13. Leahy, B., **Ong**, **D.**, Cheng, X., & Cohen, I. (March 2012). Anisotropic Diffusion of Colloidal Particles in a Shear Flow. Presented by B. Leahy at the American Physical Society March Meeting 2012, Boston, MA.
- 12. **Ong**, **D. C.**, Cheng, X., & Cohen, I. (June 2011). Enhanced and diminished diffusion of dimer particles by oscillatory shear. Talk given at the 11th New York Complex Matter Workshop, Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY.
- 11. **Ong, D. C.** (April 2011). Serial Reciprocity: What makes us want to "Pass It On"? Poster presented at the 26th Annual Spring Undergraduate Research Forum, Cornell Undergraduate Research

- Board, Ithaca, NY.
- Ong, D. C., Cheng, X., & Cohen, I. (April 2011). Tumbling Motion of Brownian Dimer Particles under Shear. Poster presented at the 26th Annual Spring Undergraduate Research Forum, Cornell Undergraduate Research Board, Ithaca, NY.
- 9. **Ong, D. C.**, (April 2011). Serial Reciprocity: What makes us want to "Pass It On"? Talk given at the Hunter R. Rawlings III Cornell Presidential Research Scholars Senior Expo, Ithaca, NY.
- 8. **Ong, D. C.** (April 2011). Serial Reciprocity: What makes us want to "Pass It On"? Talk given at the National Conference on Undergraduate Research 2011, Ithaca College, Ithaca, NY.
- 7. **Ong**, **D. C.**, Cheng, X., & Cohen, I. (April 2011). Tumbling motion of Brownian Symmetric-Dimer Colloidal Particles under Shear. Talk given at the National Conference on Undergraduate Research 2011, Ithaca College, Ithaca, NY.
- 6. **Ong**, **D. C.**, Gerbode, S., & Cohen, I. (June 2010). Of Zippers and Restricted Dislocations in colloidal crystals of spheres and dimers. Talk given at the 10th New York Complex Matter Workshop, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY.
- 5. **Ong, D. C.,** Gerbode, S., & Cohen, I. (April 2010). Peanuts and Oranges: Dislocation Dynamics in mixed crystals of dimers and spheres. Talk and poster presentation at the 25th Annual Spring Undergraduate Research Forum, Cornell Undergraduate Research Board, Ithaca, NY.
- 4. Gerbode, S., **Ong, D.**, Agarwal, U., Liddell, C., Escobedo, F., & Cohen, I. (March 2010). Glassy Dislocation Relaxation in Colloidal Peanut Crystals. Presented by S. Gerbode at the American Physical Society March Meeting 2010, Portland, OR.
- 3. **Ong, D. C.,** Gerbode, S., & Cohen, I. (May 2009). From Oranges to Peanuts to Pears: Packing in asymmetric dimer colloids. Talk given at the ICAM-I2CAM Soft Active Matter Workshop / 8th New York Complex Matter Workshop, Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY.
- 2. **Ong**, **D. C.**, Gerbode, S., & Cohen, I. (April 2009). Spheres, Pears and Peanuts: Packing in asymmetric dimer colloids. Talk and poster presentation given at the 24th Annual Spring Undergraduate Research Forum, Cornell Undergraduate Research Board, Ithaca, NY.
- 1. **Ong**, **D. C.**, Gerbode, S., & Cohen, I. (Dec 2008). Dislocations in Colloidal Dimer Crystals. Talk given at the 7th New York Complex Matter Workshop, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY.

Teaching Experience

- 7. Teaching Assistant, Psych 204: Computation and Cognition: The Probabilistic Approach (Graduate) Stanford University, Spring, 2015. Instructor: Noah D. Goodman
- 6. Teaching Assistant, Psych 254: Lab in Experimental Methods (Graduate) Stanford University, Winter, 2015. Instructor: Michael C. Frank
- 5. Teaching Assistant, Psych 90: Intro to Clinical Psychology (Undergraduate) Stanford University, Fall 2014. Instructor: Ian Gotlib
- 4. Teaching Assistant, Psych 80: Intro to Personality and Affective Science (Undergraduate) Stanford University, Spring 2014. Instructor: Jeanne Tsai
- 3. Teaching Fellow, Psych 1: Intro to Psychology (Undergraduate)
 Stanford University, Winter 2014. Instructors: Jamil Zaki, Bridgette Hard
- 2. Teaching Fellow, Psych 1: Intro to Psychology (Undergraduate)
 Stanford University, Fall 2013. Instructors: James Gross, Bridgette Hard
- 1. Physics Tutor, Physics Learning Strategies Center, Cornell University, 2010-2011

 Provided supplementary help for students taking freshman and sophomore-level physics classes

Training and Courses attended

- 3. Learning by Design: Designing Courses for Effective Student Learning, September 2016 Stanford Graduate Summer Institute; Organized by the Vice Provost for Graduate Education, taught and sponsored by the Vice Provost for Teaching & Learning, Stanford
- 2. Summer Workshop in Computational Social Science, September 2013

 Organized by the Institute for Research in the Social Sciences (IRiSS), Stanford University
- 1. RIKEN Brain Sciences Institute Summer Programme, July 2012
 Travel Grant awarded by the A*Star Graduate Academy

Professional Services

Faculty Search Committee, Stanford University Department of Psychology, Cognitive Area, 2014-2015

Graduate Admissions Committee, Stanford University Department of Psychology, Affective Science Area, 2013-2014

Area Seminar Committee, Stanford University Department of Psychology.

Cognitive Area, 2014-2015 Affective Science Area, 2013-2014

Ad-hoc reviewer.

Journals: Cognition, Psychological Science, Optical Engineering Conferences: Cognitive Science Society (CogSci), Society for Philosophy and Psychology (SPP), Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)

Professional Memberships

- 2014 Cognitive Science Society
- 2013 Society for Personality and Social Psychology (SPSP)
- 2014 Society for Affective Science (SAS)

References

Noah D. Goodman

Associate Professor of Psychology, Computer Science (courtesy), and Linguistics (courtesy)

Stanford University

Department of Psychology Jordan Hall, Building 01-420 450 Serra Mall Stanford, CA 94305

ngoodman@stanford.edu

Jamil Zaki
Assistant Professor of Psychology
Stanford University
Department of Psychology
Jordan Hall, Building 01-420
450 Serra Mall
Stanford, CA 94305
jzaki@stanford.edu

Christopher Potts

Associate Professor of Linguistics
Director, Center for the Study of Language and Information
Stanford University
Department of Linguistics
Margaret Jacks Hall, Building 460
Stanford, CA 94305
cgpotts@stanford.edu